Imagine if there was a way to get clients
without having to rely on social media,
without having to be a whiz at editing
or understand how to use Instagram.
Do you do a carousel? A reel?
Are you supposed to add music?
For some of you, you have a business,
you have needs, you have requirements, and
you just don't have the luxury of spending
the next three, six, nine months
learning all of these things.
The good news, I feel, is this.
Every single person now
is running to social media and looking to
build a personal brand so they can make
money remote from their laptop
in Bali, which is great.
It's what I teach people to do.
But I think it's important
that we also teach people there
are other mediums in
which we can acquire new business,
and better yet, those mediums are being
massively overlooked, which
is going to create some kind of
opportunity.
If everyone is going one way to try
and get Insta-famous to build their
business,
some of the old bricks and mortar,
bread and butter means
are being overlooked, and
we're going to go into some of them now.
Quickly before that,
just let me explain how this video came
about, and there's
something you can learn from this.
Funnily enough,
a lot of my ideas for these videos on this
channel come from
interactions I have with people.
So that's lesson number one.
If you have people coming to you asking
questions, when you do come to making
content in the future, they
are the things you should talk about.
There are personal trainers out there
that have clients saying, "What is a
macronutrient? How do I lose fat,
and why do I raise my heels in a squat?"
But
then when they go to social media,
they think they should do,
"Here's my workout of
the day.
Here's my lunch prep for the week."
If they only listen to the people
asking them questions,
they could make better content,
but that's a different
swerve tangent. There
was a chap called Charlie,
who I competed against in
Brazilian jujitsu.
He's a high-level brown belt,
and I beat him in the first
match.
I actually used so much effort trying to
stop him from
leg locking me that I
was gassed to the point,
here's a picture of me lying on the
mat, completely exhausted.
And then I had to face him again in the
weight division,
where he beat me twice in a row in two
separate matches in under
30 seconds. But ever since that,
I've been following Charlie on social
media.
He's been following me,
and we're both at the same competition at
the weekend, and
he comes to me with some business
questions.
His first question was, "James,
can you help me?" My first response was,
"I'm not
sure. What is the business
that you have?" Charlie's business
is air conditioning,
which I have no experience in.
I sometimes stare at air conditioning
units and
think,
"How do they work?" Similar to a fridge.
Find myself next to a fridge going,
"How do you work?
I know you run through electricity,
but what is happening for
electricity to make things cold?" I can
understand electricity making things hot.
The production of light.
Is it 95% of light is heat? I don't know.
But how does electricity make things cold?
I lay in bed awake at night trying to
figure these things out.
Probably should ask Charlie.
But even though I know nothing about the
air
conditioning business,
first question I asked him
was the first question that I
would ask you.
What does a customer look like to you?
Because although the business
is air conditioning,
is your client someone who's
never had air conditioning,
doesn't have it, or is it someone
that has it, wants to
upgrade,
or maybe wants to have maintenance,
or someone that can come out every six
months to clean the filter?
And Charlie said to me,
"Someone who wants air
conditioning or wants it fixed." So good
news is this is a very broad spectrum.
It's not like Charlie has an air
conditioning business that only works on
medium-sized commercial properties within
a five-kilometer radius of a certain
point. So the first thing
that my brain goes to
when we eliminate social media as a
way to build his business is flyering.
Yes, flyering,
which I know can sound daft
or like something you would do 30
years ago,
but I'll explain why I think
that there could be a comeback for
flyering.
The second thing Charlie said
was about putting signage on his car.
I don't think that's a good idea.
I'll explain why in a second.
And I have the authority to do
that because I'm someone who used to have
signage on
his car when he was a personal trainer.
And first of all, my brand
was called James Smith Training.
And do you know how many clients I got
from that signage sticker on the back of
my
car? None. Nada. Just meant that
if I parked in disabled,
people knew it was park
and disabled. Anyway, back to the flyer.
Biggest mistake I see with flyers
is some people think
that they can design a flyer
on whatever program it is,
Microsoft Paint, by the looks of it.
I'm like, "Listen, brother,
stop doing it on Microsoft Paint."
And also, to any of
you watching this video, chances
are the majority of you,
I think about 70%, are
blokes. We've all tried,
through our single years,
to make a nice-looking
bed. Try getting a little European pillow.
We try chucking a throw on it.
Always looks dog shit.
When it comes to design, men, we
are awful.
When it comes to arranging
and designing a front room,
it has a La-Z-Boy
sofa and a TV. And if you're like me,
you're probably someone that thinks, "Oh,
a
beer fridge would look good in here."
When it comes to design, hire someone.
Go on Fiverr. Go on Upwork.
Ask your friend who's a designer to make
it look
nice.
And if you haven't got the budget for
that, get your missus to do it.
I've got a few guys
that I worked with this week in the
mentorship where quite
literally I saw their landing pages,
and I said, "Hey,
can you get your girlfriend
to have a look at this?" Lo and behold,
comes back, looks way better.
They just have the eye for it. Now,
the flyer doesn't have to explain
when you got
your qualification,
how long you've been a mechanic,
that you used to swim for
county.
It doesn't have to have the branding of
the business, and it just needs to
have a few things. One,
I think it's a good idea to have an offer,
promise, and
some form of humanization.
Is humanization a word? I don't know.
So let's look at some context for the
offer.
For an air conditioning business,
I think you could say,
"We will come to your
house and give you a free quote.
Not only that,
we will give you a design spec of
what we think would be right for your
house, whether it's ducted air con,
whether
it is a..." I don't know much about air
con.
"Whether it's a unit
that goes on the wall.
We could do a bit of feng shui.
Hey, because the entrance to your house
is there,
we think the unit should go here.
That does mean that it's going to be a
little bit more expensive.
However,
if we do fit the unit over there..."
[horn honks]
Fuckers. So a free quotation, and in
that you could say no obligation,
because you
don't want some slimy salesperson coming
around your house going, "Sign up now.
Buy now. There's 10% off.
If I leave this house,
you're going to have to pay more."
So an offer.
Some form of promise I think
is another great idea.
Something with air con
is a little bit more difficult.
You can't say, "This
is the coldest you're ever going to be,
or you get your money
back," because you could be exploited.
But the promise could be,
"We vouch to have your air conditioning
project finished
within two weeks of sending you the
quote." Timely.
In Australia, we're approaching summer.
That could be the very thing
that gets that person over the edge.
People are impatient. I'm impatient.
When I buy things online, it's like, hey,
$5 postage, $10
postage, $45 postage same day. I'm like,
sold.
Sometimes I think about hiring Uber
drivers to go get things.
You know,
you could pick it up the same day.
I'll just... Anyway.
And just before I get into the
humanization point,
let's look into other contexts.
Brazilian jujitsu, an offer.
First week free, first month free. Great.
The promise that it will be a safe
session, that they won't feel intimidated,
that
they could make new friends,
that it's something that they could enjoy,
that it
could be the future of their training.
Coaching of any kind.
Your offer could be,
"Come train with me for free.
Come train with me for a week for free."
And again, before you think that giving
someone a week of your time could be
crazy, we'll get onto that in a second.
And a promise.
We will work towards your weight loss
or fat loss goals, and if we
do not accomplish what we set out within
the first month, I give you a full 100%
money-back guarantee. These
are also point of differences.
So the offer and the promise
are very important to put on there.
Now, the next point that I would call
is humanization. Okay?
I'm not even sure if that's a word,
but anyway.
When it comes to the flyering,
something that I've got someone to do
before is to
put something like the first thing on it
saying, "I hope you don't mind
that my son or my daughter put this
through your letterbox." Oh, wow.
Someone is out there not just proactively
looking for business, they're out there
with their kids.
Their kid put it through the letterbox.
Suddenly it doesn't feel so slimy
and so dirty.
Another thing is,
if you're flyering your local area,
if you've got a geographic
thing, you might even have a yoga
or a Pilates studio,
you want to get the people
within a five-kilometer
or three-mile radius in the onset,
because they're just
going to find it easier to get there.
There's not going to be so many barriers
to being a regular customer of yours
because of geographic distances.
You could even then,
on the humanization scale,
put your street name.
"Hey,
I live over on Hall Street." They go,
"I know Hall Street." "And I'm setting
up a Pilates studio,
and I thought it'd be rude for me to do so
without just
letting you know about it.
So I hope you don't mind
that my daughters and I, this
evening,
came and put this into your letterbox."
And you could be area specific.
Rather than just saying, "Our studio
is in North Bondi," you can have this
effect,
I don't know what it's called,
but have you ever noticed
that you go on holiday,
let's say,
you're doing a cruise in Benidorm,
knowing you, and you're there, you're
having a few beers. You're like, "Oh,
yeah.
You come here often?" All that usual chat.
You say to them, "Where
are you from?" They say,
"Sunderland." "We're from
Sunderland as well. Trish, Trish,
they're from Sunderland as well.
What's the chances of that? Small world.
What a small world. Can you believe it?
Do you know a Dave
and Leroy?" "I know a Dave
and Leroy." "Oh, my God, we
know Trish. You know a Dave
and Leroy." Before you know it,
you're best friends.
Why? Because you're from the same area.
Same way that if you were...
There's something,
I could be making this up,
where people are more likely
to let you out at a junction
if it's the same model of car because
you've got some
familiarity between you.
Every time there's a glitch in the matrix,
suddenly you're
being more generous to people. "No,
you get out. Love the car, mate.
Love the car." Probably not a GT3, is it?
But you know what I'm saying.
So if you can humanize yourself,
even put a bit of vulnerability in there.
"Hi, my name's James.
I've opened a brand-new Brazilian jujitsu
studio.
I'm really hoping over the next three to
six months to grow this to the size that I
can do this as my dream job
and leave my corporate job of
recruitment." Suddenly
they go, "Wow,
this person's taking a risk in life.
I'm going to go because I'm going to make
his dream a reality." So rather than
trying to seem perfect and corporate,
humanize yourself.
"Hey,
after 40 years in the corporate world,
I want to pursue my dream of having my
own Pilates studio.
I want to work with ladies
that want to work on
remaining strong and offset an injury
or whatever it is." So they can read that
flyer and not feel like they're being sold
to.
They can feel like they're being spoken
Case in point, recently,
my missus says to me,
two young lads came round
promoting their car detailing business.
I said, "Have you got a card?" She says,
"Yeah." Cool.
Got the card, called them up. I said,
"Come round, do two cars." Didn't even ask
how much it was. I like the hustle.
They came to the door, they
were polite to my
partner, and they just said, "Hey,
if you need your cars washed,
we're going to do
it." When they turned up, I was like,
"How old are you boys?" 17 and 20.
Amazing.
Great. There's the Golf, there's the Audi.
Let me know how much it is.
If that was an ad on social media
or a video, I wouldn't have cared.
But the fact they took the care
and attention, they were local lads,
they were
young, they were little hustlers,
I loved it.
When they told me how much it was, it
was heinously expensive.
What even is car detailing? It
is glorified polishing.
I've got the PVC wraps on the cars. Like,
I've got...
They're plastic wrapped, the cars.
So they got all this expensive polish,
and I'm like, "Mate, I've done myself in
here." They're like, "Oh,
we'll get the right..." It's plastic.
You're washing plastic.
So I won't be using them again, but still,
they made a few
hundred bucks, let's say that.
So one of the things that I think
is really
important with this whole topic is
that you need to be proactive,
and we could even
call that proactivity.
So Declan over here,
the lad who's going to edit this video,
he got his job by being proactive enough
to make videos for my barber for free.
So then when I was at my barber's
complaining about how my videographer
before was
retarded.
People say you can't use the word retarded
anymore, but I'm bringing it
back. Trump's in office.
The word retarded is back. He
was retarded.
My barber goes, "Mate, there's a lad
that I've been working with.
You should meet him." I met him.
Now Declan's here being heinously
overpaid.
Best paid 23-year-old in all of New South
Wales.
Also, when I started my PT business,
before I had the social media following,
I was
proactive by going into local businesses.
I actually was at a business event,
and I was talking about how maybe the...
Is that you, Liam?
Every time I'm trying to make content,
he's bowling here.
I was fucking one lane.
All right. Just give us a minute,
all right?
I used to have the same excuses as you,
bro, saying, "Oh, there's just not much
opportunity in my area." And I was asked,
"Oh, James, where's the gym you work in?"
I was like, "Bracknell." They were like,
"Oh, there's a big business park in
Bracknell. How far
are you from that?" I was like,
"I'm in it.
I'm right slap bang in the middle of
that technology park, brother." He goes,
"Oh,
so you're telling me there's no local
businesses that you could walk into in
your
lunch break and ask them
if they wanted a free seminar on fat
loss?" Said, "I
probably could do that." I shit you not,
the very first business I went
into, they were like, "Oh,
we'd love that." Booked me in.
Now, there were only about 11 people
that turned up to it, but they gave me a
little boardroom. 11 people came in.
That was my biggest crowd at that point.
11 people were there.
I got to practice the process of giving my
first talk, and at the end of it,
three of them inquired about PT, and two
of them ended up as clients.
So I didn't have to go into
that business and ask
that. But for so many of you,
are there businesses?
Are there technology parks?
And again,
there'd be different flyers for this.
The ones that go out to residential might
say, "Hey, me and my daughters, me and my
kids", or just the,
"I've been in your area from a local road
giving out things.
Are you interested?" From a commercial
standpoint, "Hey, my name's James.
I'm a personal trainer.
For the next six months,
I'm taking two hours out of my day
to approach local businesses to educate
their workforce how they can eat better
and
train more so that, one, they can feel
and look better, but two, so they
can be more productive in the workforce."
The businesses go in, "Let's book him in.
It's going to cost us nothing, and
if them lot could be less fat,
we could get more
work out of them." Then they go to HR,
and HR go to people and say, "Hey, guys,
we really care about the levels of health
and wellbeing and
mental health in our office. So for
that reason, we've gone to large
expense to get in a health expert to help
you guys with your
diet." That's how the corporate thing
works.
So from a productivity standpoint,
humanization standpoint, these are great.
These things can get an emotional
connection.
Putting something on the side of your car
isn't. It's just not.
And I would say this is a bias thing,
because me and my partner were driving,
and
we did need a dog trainer,
and the car in front of us had dog trainer
signage on it, and I said, "This
is a sign from the universe.
This is the sign from a God almighty
above." I'm not religious.
So we called him, said, "Look,
we need a dog trainer." He was dog shit.
Didier Dog Shit. He
was the worst dog trainer in the world.
So maybe I am biased to that.
He came round with the dog, got a treat.
"Oh, sit, good boy. Oh yeah, paw,
good boy." I'm like,
"We've already taught him
that. He's not a problem in the house,
brother. He's a problem out in that park.
You can't come round, charge us all
that money just to give our dog treats on
the
balcony." Anyway, moving on. Now,
paid ads can circumnavigate
social media,
because you can just peer-to-peer,
as they say.
You could just pay for traffic to go to
your website,
pay for traffic to go to your
landing page,
pay for traffic to go to your squeeze
page, whatever it is.
However,
I do like people to master organic first.
Don't just see paid ads as the lady with
the red dress in the Matrix that walks
past and takes your eye line. If you
are going to get into the paid ads,
I would
recommend that you get good at organic
content, because your ability to conduct
yourself, get your point across,
everything you need to do in a paid ad,
also, you
need to get good at in organic content.
So trust me, if you
are going to do paid ads,
it needs to be synergistic with
organic content. Not to mention
that people often, through paid ads,
want to see
some social proof. If you're someone
that just turned up in a paid ad, they're
like,
"I want to know more about this person.
If I'm going to spend my money,
I want to see this person move
and do other
things." And if you've got a dormant,
dead social media profile, and you're
spending loads in paid ads,
when they come to your page
and you haven't posted in
six weeks, they're going to think,
"This person's a charlatan,
who's going to run
away with my money." So you do really need
to make sure that if you're going to do
paid,
strategy needs to be coupled with organic.
I'm just saying it.
What about referrals?
When I say to people,
"So how do you grow and market your
business?" And they say, "Referrals."
That just says to me that
that person doesn't
have a fucking clue about marketing.
Because in my line of work,
and most other people's line of works,
referrals are
dog shit. I hate them. Liam,
you ever get any good referrals? No.
So any time someone says referrals,
because again, when you have a customer or
someone with you that's really good
or whatever, when you say, "Oh,
have you got
any friends that might be right?" Although
they might have one or two, they haven't
got the same level of emotional connection
to you.
Just because someone goes, "Oh,
my neighbor could be perfect." Their
neighbor is
going to be 10 times harder to convert
into a customer than them.
You're way better off to use other
channels to win that person over.
Now, when it comes to business,
I hate terminologies where people just
throw
letters around. They're like, "Oh,
what's the ROAS on that,
Sally?" Stop using
terminologies to appear smart. There
are a few that we just need to understand
from
the off. Cost per acquisition. Now,
when we look at this,
CPI, if you did a flyering campaign
and you spend $300 on
flyers and it's an afternoon of your time
but you acquire two new clients, you need
to then look at how much you had to pay to
acquire new business.
And then ideally it would be good to
understand how much in monetary terms
that new
business is worth to you. So for instance,
for my business mentorship, the average
client spends a fair whack of money.
So our cost per acquisition can be high.
It could be $100 and it would still be
fine.
But the reason that this would be so much
harder for my fitness business is, first
of all,
we charge a lot less for the fitness
business, affordable online coaching.
Not only that,
we then need to fulfill other expenses,
app store, app
development, coaching costs. So therefore,
if we acquire a client that spends
$100,
we can't spend more than $20 to acquire
that person, or we don't make any
money.
So we need to understand roughly through
these means of acquiring new
business,
what the cost per acquisition is.
If the average customer spend,
what the average person spends with you,
and the
cost per acquisition is below that,
happy days.
Now, if you're a personal trainer
or a fitness coach, like, "Oh,
I might put £10
a day on ads." Listen,
if your average client
is spending £40 an hour with you and
they're buying 10 blocks,
let's say the average person only did 10
sessions, that's
£400.
If you could spend £100 acquiring
that person, that's
great. But if you're someone
that then goes, "Oh,
my average client spends six
months with me." Six months at two
sessions a week.
If someone trains with me twice a week
and they've trained with me for six
months,
how many sessions would that be?
That's 52, isn't it? Six months? Yeah, 52.
I did the math. It didn't work. What
is 52 times 40? That's 2,000 pounds.
2,000 pounds,
you should easily be able to allocate 10%
of that.
You say, "Oi,
we are now as a coaching business,
happy to spend 200 pounds to
acquire one client." That's crazy.
No, it's not,
because the average person stays for six
months, two sessions a week.
Bersh. Next terminology to get into
is just the return on investment, which is
similar to that. For how much we spend,
what do we get back?
With the flyering campaign,
if you spend $300 and only make $300,
you can
say maybe that campaign doesn't work.
If your hourly rate for coaching is £40,
but you have to spend two hours of going
around giving out flyers to make
that money back,
it's not a good use of time,
because the return on investment just
isn't there.
Then the last thing we need to look at,
the ROAS that I mentioned before is return
on ad spend.
So if you spend so much on ads,
how much do you get back?
And this isn't always the simplest thing
to quantify, because you might spend
money on ads now
that might get someone to go to your
website, but then it might
take them a couple of weeks to actually
make the decision,
or they might have slept
on it,
or they might have come into the physical
location and signed up and not
signed through the website.
So ROAS isn't always a very good and
accurate means of determining exactly
return on ad spend.
Someone just helped themselves to an tonic
downstairs.
It's a sign of a good product, that.
Ultimately, through these different means,
you also run multiple campaigns and find
out what works, what doesn't, what
is efficient, what isn't,
what returns well on
your cash. Because ultimately,
if you go out with your kids
and you spend $300
on flyers and you make thousands of
dollars of business,
you should get everyone's
kids.
You say to all your friends in your
network, "Oi, let me hire your
15-year-olds.
I'm going to give them $20 an hour.
They're going to go flyering."
But just make sure they don't hire kids
like me when
I was younger,
because I'd probably just chuck them all
in a bin and set them
alight and told them I'd put them through
the letterbox.
So make sure you trust the right people
with that.
Basically, the main point of the video
is marketing doesn't always have to be
through social media,
but we can learn a lot from fingering.
Yes, fingering.
Gen Z don't even finger anymore.
He probably doesn't.
The young kids don't do it like we used to
do it back in the day.
But ultimately,
no one really knows what they're doing
fingering. They don't.
And the only way you're going to get
better at it is to do it more.
And fingering different people should
elicit different responses because all
vaginas, or maybe bum holes,
I don't know which way you like to finger,
are
different.
And it's only through trying things you
find little different
trends. Maybe feeding the pony,
maybe saying,
"Come here." Maybe giving the
pneumatic drill. Whatever it is
that you want to do,
you can find out patterns
that emerge, what works, what doesn't,
what gets a good response, what gets a
terrible response,
and only over time then can you become the
master fingerer.
So hopefully for any of you
that navigate in the world of social media
that maybe
aren't quite sure if there's a means
or a way to get more clients or get more
business, ultimately try everything.
Allocate a small amount of funds to it.
Whichever one works, double down on it,
expand on it.
And which ones don't, pull them back.
Be creative.
This is actually probably a golden
opportunity to go for non-traditional
means
rather than a hindrance. Links
are in the description as per always.
Hope you enjoyed that,
and YouTube will probably recommend you
watch this video,
and this one will change your life because
YouTube's a smart bugger as per usual.
I hope you enjoy
that one as much as you enjoyed this.
Bye-bye.